Guide to the William Martin Religious Right research collection, 1975-2000 MS 537
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series II: Subject files, 1978-1996 (Boxes 77-91)
  - Subseries A: Alphabetical subject files
    - Bork, Robert (Box 77, Folder 19)
      - Bork, Robert (Research Leads) (Box 77, Folder 19, Subfolder 2)
    - Brandt, Ed (Box 77, Folder 20)
      Selection of a book entitled "Paving the Road" from 1981.
    - Bryant, Anita (Box 77, Folder 21)
      A number of articles about Anita Bryant's divorce, and some from the rest of her life outside her divorce.
    - Buchanan, Patrick (Box 77, Folder 22)
      - Buchanan, Pat and Clinton (Box 77, Folder 22, Subfolder 1)
        Background on Buchanan by the American Jewish Committee and a Buchanan speech on Bill Clinton.
      - Buchanan, Patrick (Box 77, Folder 22, Subfolder 2)
        A number of articles written by Pat Buchanan including from the Washington Times, and a newsletter written by him for The American Cause, a newsletter.
    - Bush, George (Box 77, Folder 23)
      - Bush Administration (Box 77, Folder 23, Subfolder 1)
        Articles throughout the first Bush's administration, including on the 1992 election. A lot on the role of Pat Buchanan in the administration. Some notes on the news articles, which focus on religion in the Bush administration.
      - Bush, George (including 1988 election) (Box 77, Folder 23, Subfolder 2)
        News articles on Bush's religion and politics.
    - California - Arts, 1990 (Box 77, Folder 24)
      A large number of photocopied news articles about the role of evangelicalism in California politics and the National Endowment for the Arts. Also includes notes on California's evangelical political groups. Rejection of the NEA funding by a number of CA organizations because of its views.
    - California Education, 1990 (Box 77, Folder 25)
      A number of articles about the role of religion in public school education inside California. Debates over creationism.
    - California Arts, 1991 (Box 77, Folder 26)
      Scanned newspaper articles about censorship and religion in California political life.
    - California Education, 1991 (Box 77, Folder 27)
      News about the debates over public school textbooks and the role of religion in public schools.
    - California Arts, 1992 (Box 78, Folder 1)
      A large number of scanned articles from all of 1992 about the role of religion in public life, Pat Buchanan, and specifically religion in the arts. From LA Times, San Francisco Chronicle, San Jose Mercury etc.
    - California - Education (1 of 2), 1992 (Box 78, Folder 2)
      A large number of scanned articles from across 1992 about California and the role of religion in public education. Both large and small city newspapers. Book banning, sex education, and evolution in school.
    - California - Education (2 of 2), 1992 (Box 78, Folder 3)
      Scattershot of interplay of religion and education in California in news.
    - California Religious Right (Box 78, Folder 4)
      Series of articles from 1991-1992 about the rise and structure of the Religious Right in California. Articles are both pro and anti-religious right. Rise of the religious right within the state's Reupblican Party. Booklet from the liberal advocacy group-People for the American Way (1993-95).
    - Campbell, Phillip (Box 78, Folder 5)
      A liberal minister in Table Mesa.
    - Campus Crusade (Box 78, Folder 6)
      - André Kole Ministry (Box 78, Folder 6, Subfolder 1)
        Magician and minister. Couple of emails and flyers about evangelizing on college campuses.
      - Jack McDowell Ministry (Box 78, Folder 6, Subfolder 2)
        Information for a new documentary on the History of the Evangelical Christian Movement, from McDowell, a minister.
    - Capitol Hill Prayer Alert (Box 78, Folder 7)
      Series of flyers, newsletters, and pamphlets about the the 1993 Health Care Act, and fears over abortion, the Clintons, and LGBTQ+ individuals.
    - Carter, Jimmy (1 of 2) (Box 78, Folder 8)
      - Carter, Jimmy (Box 78, Folder 8, Subfolder 1)
        Research summaries from archival research about Jimmy Carter, and Birth of an Idea...Secular.
      - Jesus Film Project - CCC (Box 78, Folder 8, Subfolder 2)
        Folder from the Jesus Film Project including information on how to evangelize with the material. There are some images and background information on the project.
      - SNL - Carter/Playboy (Box 78, Folder 8, Subfolder 3)
        Summaries of Saturday Night Live sketches featuring portrayals of President Jimmy Carter made in the mid 90s from the mid 70s.
      - WSB - U of Georgia - Carter (Box 78, Folder 8, Subfolder 4)
        Information from the WSB television news video archive. List of newsfilm archive material associated with Jimmy Carter from the mid-1970s.
    - Carter, Jimmy (2 of 2) (Box 78, Folder 9)
      - Evangelical Voting Stats (Box 78, Folder 9, Subfolder 1)
        There is data from the 1968-1976 general elections that showed a swing from Nixon to Carter between 1972-1976. Some more data from the 1980s as well.
      - Greider on Carter (Box 78, Folder 9, Subfolder 2)
        Articles written by the Washington Post Magazine writer William Greider about Jimmy Carter. From the late 1970s to 1980.
      - Jody Powell (Box 78, Folder 9, Subfolder 3)
        Powell was part of Carter's staff and his press secretary, including a page long biography of Powell's life.
      - Carter "Family" Transcripts (Box 78, Folder 9, Subfolder 4)
        Series of statements and White House documents from Jimmy Carter about the role of the family and personal views on religion among other things.
    - Catholics and Religious Right (Box 78, Folder 12)
      Couple of unknown book pages on the role and fit of Roman Catholics within the rising religious right.
    - Catholics for Free Choice (Box 78, Folder 10)
      Two booklets on birth control and public perception in the Catholics for a Free Choice series.
    - Catholic Worker (Box 78, Folder 11)
      Newspaper edition from the Catholic Worker from September, 1989. Original newspaper, socialist or marxist paper, considering itself a Christian anarchist publication
    - Christian Action Council (Box 78, Folder 13)
      Coalition and international boycott of corporations from donating money to Planned Parenthood in September 1990.
    - Christian Action Network (Box 78, Folder 14)
      A number of statements by the president of the Christian Action Network, a lot of news articles, and a Federal Election Commission complaint by the DNC against the Christian Action Network and booklets from the 1994 CAN Government Report Card.
    - Christian Citizen (Box 78, Folder 15)
      Two pamphlets from an evangelical Christian political organization.
    - Christian Coalition (1 of 5) (Box 78, Folder 16)
      - NYC Christian Coalition (Box 78, Folder 16, Subfolder 1)
        Articles with annotations on a variety of topics within the religious right Culture War, Church and State, and notes about a documentary.
      - Texas Christian Coalition (Box 78, Folder 16, Subfolder 2)
        Newspaper scans, American Family Association newsletters, and other examples of the power of the Christian Coalition in Texas.
      - Reed, Ralph (Box 78, Folder 16, Subfolder 3)
        Series of scanned news articles about Ralph Reed, the first executive director of the Christian Coalition. Also a feature from the Washington Post magazine from January 1996 and other various articles.
      - Marshall Whitman (Box 78, Folder 16, Subfolder 4)
        Whitman was a Jewish lobbyist for the Christian Coalition, including a couple of news articles.
    - Christian Coalition (2 of 5) (Box 78, Folder 17)
      Role of Christian Coalition seen through news articles, some original newspapers that discuss training christians to become municipal politicians. There was also instructions on grassroots politics and pieces by Ralph Reed Jr., an attendance list of Christian Coalition meeting, and news articles from the early 1990s, Christian Coalition piece from Pat Robertson.
    - Christian Coalition (3 of 5) (Box 78, Folder 18)
      Similar news reports, radio reports, and anti-Anti-Defamation League reports. There was both anti and pro Christian Coalition pieces alongside some written by Christian Coalition. Also, two copies of transcripts from Pat Robertson's Christian Coalition "Road to Victory" conference, religious rights political strategies both locally and nationally against Clinton-Gore, polling of the religious right.
    - Christian Coalition (4 of 5) (Box 78, Folder 19)
      - Christian Coalition Printed Matter (Box 78, Folder 19, Subfolder 1)
        Christian Coalition flyers, booklets, and original newspapers. 1996 Christian Coalition election magazine, most Christian Coalition New York material and anti-Christian Coalition material from the Interfaith Alliance and Americans United for Separation of Church and State (1995-09).
      - Marshall Wittman (Box 78, Folder 19, Subfolder 2)
        Christian Coalition lobbyist who is Jewish.
      - Dick Weinhold (Box 78, Folder 19, Subfolder 3)
        Leader of the Texas Christian Coalition, scanned news articles and a chapter from a book entitled Texas: An Emergence of the Christian Right
      - Guy Rodgers (Box 78, Folder 19, Subfolder 4)
        A campaign manager of the Pat Buchannan's 1996 campaign. Newspaper transcripts and a original from The Nation.
      - Tom DeLay (Box 78, Folder 19, Subfolder 5)
        Article from the Wall Street Journal from DeLay, an anti-regulatory individual on business, which is supported by Christian Coalition, Contract with America
      - Christian Coalition (Box 78, Folder 19, Subfolder 6)
        Pieces from Christian Coalition, hand-written notes from Martin, Religion and Politics from USA Weekend, Ralph Reed newspaper articles.
    - Christian Coalition (5 of 5) (Box 78, Folder 20)
      Training seminar and voting records from the 102nd (1991-1992) congress all from the early 1990s, mostly 1992 election materials. Christian Coalition was as if not more powerful than the Moral Majority in the 1980s
    - Christian Coalition: Wildernet (Box 78, Folder 21)
      Time magazine cover story about Ralph Reed with notes from William Martin, NPR transcripts and Charlie Rose interview of Ralph Reed. Also there was a annotated edition of the "Road to Victory" presentation.
    - Christian Life Commission (Box 79, Folder 1)
      Pamphlet from the Christian Life Commission of the Southern Baptist Convention in Nashville.
    - Christian Rights Activists (Box 79, Folder 2)
      List of both activists and leaders of the Christian right for contacts for the film. Scanned, handwritten notes about these activists.
    - IRS v. Christian Schools, 1978 (Box 79, Folder 3)
      Some newspaper that needs scanning, selection from the book "God and Jimmy Carter," notes from "The Right Woman," news transcripts, an article from the Journal of Research on Christian Education, and 1985 article entitled The New Christian Right in American. There is also a few other articles including Attitudes Toward Church and State.
    - Christian Values in Action Coalition (Box 79, Folder 4)
      Pamphlet from the Action Coalition, the Traditional Values in Action Resource Directory, and emails between Coalition members.
    - Chronology Info (Box 79, Folder 5)
      National Organization for Women information, chronology of the 20th century about the rise of evangelicals in the political sphere of America. Socio-cultural and economic chronology of Reagan's second term.
    - Church and State (Box 79, Folder 6)
      A number of newspaper articles, New York Times National Report article from 1996/01/15 and another New York Times article from 1993/09/16 between religion and politics. Scanned newspaper articles from the Times and a scanned article from the Michigan Law Review from 1991. All about creating the line between church and state.
    - Civil Rights (1 of 2) (Box 79, Folder 7)
      - Civil Rights-Falwell (Box 79, Folder 7, Subfolder 1)
        Scanned book from Nixon and articles from Falwell along with from Word of Life. There was also a homemade timeline of Falwell during the Civil Rights era. There was also a transcript from Falwell's Press Conference and scans of Harding's Field Notes, scanned Lynchburg Daily stories from 1985 with handwritten content list. Also included Jerry Falwell's 1985 fact sheet syllabus on South Africa, New York Times articles about Falwell and Tutu.
      - Civil Rights (Box 79, Folder 7, Subfolder 2)
        Handwritten notes from the 1995, notes on Will Campbell, and Faxes from LaShaune Fitch, the Associate Producer of the Lumiere Productions inc. Also, articles from the "Moral Majority" in 1987/12. 1980 Fall from The Public Interest, a number of scanned news articles, a chapter on Race and Southern Baptists, and an article about Southern Baptists and Race Relations, 1947-1977: Changing Attitudes from Harry Truman to Jimmy Carter (1978). Other journal articles about Civil Rights among white Southern clergy, scanned New York Times news articles.
    - Civil Rights (2 of 2) (Box 79, Folder 8)
      - Civil Rights - Lynchburg (Box 79, Folder 8, Subfolder 1)
        Scan of "A Legacy of Learning: The Lynchburg Public Schools 1871-1986," a handwritten series of notes from "A Chapter in Lynchburg's History with handwritten timeline, and a transcript of an interview of Rebecca Owen (White student that participated in the sit-ins) by Carolyn Bell. There is also a draft of a article by Carolyn Wilkerson Bell about the 1960 sit-ins, the Lynchburg Civil Rights Chronology, and a Compilation Chronology etc.
      - Lynchburg Civil Rights Newspaper Articles (Box 79, Folder 8, Subfolder 2)
        Scanned newspaper articles about Lynchburg race relations and segregation scanned from the 1960s-1980s.
    - Clinton (Box 79, Folder 9)
      Original newspaper articles from New York Times and The Nation from the Clinton presidency and its relationship with the Religious Right alongside issues like prayer in school. One headline is "Clinton Sees Place for Religion in School"
    - Coalition on Revival (Box 79, Folder 10)
    - Cole James, Kay (Box 79, Folder 11)
      Scanned newspaper articles about Cole who was the Virginia Secretary of Health and Human Resources, from 1993-1994. In addition, theres a book review of Cole's book "Never Forget."
    - Colorado for Family Values (Box 79, Folder 12)
      Information on Amendment 2, which denied protection for LGBTQ+ individuals, and against the "militant gay agenda." All material about Amendment 2 from Colorado for Family Values.
    - Colson, Chuck (Box 79, Folder 13)
      Colson is author and former political operative for Nixon turned born-again Christian.
      - Prison Fellowship Ministries (Box 79, Folder 13, Subfolder 1)
        Memo from Colson about providing church for the Children of imprisoned parents.
      - Born Again (Box 79, Folder 13, Subfolder 2)
        Transcripts of news stories from 1976-1977 about Colson's book.
    - Communism (Box 79, Folder 14)
      A number of old newspaper articles from the late 1970s and early 80s. Articles about leftists, the KKK, and the killing of 5 Communist Workers Party demonstrators along with protests by the KKK and American Nazi Party. Information about race relations and a manuscript about the history of the 1996 Christian Anti-Communism Crusade in Greensboro NC.
    - Conlan, John (Box 79, Folder 15)
      Questions for an interview with John Conlan who was an evangelical political operative.
    - Corporation for Public Broadcasting (Box 79, Folder 16)
      Survey of new public TV series from the early 1990s.
    - Council for National Policy (Box 79, Folder 17)
      News articles from mid-1990s about the Council for National Policy, which was a Republican think tank and policy maker from the Religious Right from the publication In These Times.
    - Covenant Church (Box 79, Folder 18)
      - Covenant Correspondence (Box 79, Folder 18, Subfolder 1)
        Letter from the Executive Director of Covenant Publications John Phelan.
      - The Covenant - Companion (Box 79, Folder 18, Subfolder 2)
        A number of issues of the evangelical publication from the Covenant called Companion from late 1994 to mid 1995.
    - The Creative Coalition (Box 79, Folder 19)
      Janurary 1994 of The Journal of the Creative Coalition, whcich advocated social change through the arts and a reaction to the rise of the religious right.
    - Curry, Jerry (Box 79, Folder 20)
      Email with the producer of the PBS documentary and transcripts of news about General Jerry Curry, an administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration, news articles from the Saturday Evening Post, and scans of a book "Spiritual Warfare."
    - Dobson, Ed (Box 79, Folder 21)
      Includes an article from Christianity Today entitled "His Father's Son" about James Dobson Jr. Additional highly annotated news articles about Dobson and his views on AIDS and other transcripts of news articles about Dobson.
    - Doner, Colonel (Box 79, Folder 22)
      Includes a selection of news articles focusing on the Rise of the Christian Coalition and specifically about Colonel Doner, a founder of the Christian Voice. Also copies of his writing for the Chalcedon Report in November, 1994.
    - The Door (Box 79, Folder 23)
      Issue of a satire magazine from January-February 1994 entitled the Megachurch-Christian.
    - Dornan, Robert (Box 79, Folder 24)
      Scanned article from the New York Times from June 27th, 1995 about representative Dornan, a religious right candidate for president in 1996 running against Bob Dole.
    - Elwell, Marlene (Box 79, Folder 25)
      Transcripts from news articles from the 1980s about Elwell, an anti-abortion political operative. She was Michigan coordinator of Pat Robertson's Freedom Council. Also includes a chronology of Robertson's Presidential Campaign. Elwell written about in the news throughout the Robertson political campaign during 1988.
    - ERA (Box 79, Folder 26)
      Folder includes a scanned chapter about the failure of the ERA along with a ERA and Phyllis Schlafly chronolog and notes on the book "Why the ERA failed."
    - Evangelism (Box 79, Folder 27)
      - Criswell - Evangelism (Box 79, Folder 27, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes biography of Criswell, a pastor at a large Baptist Church, along with notes on W. A. Criswell from the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary.
      - Roberta Hestenes (Box 79, Folder 27, Subfolder 2)
        Includes an article from Christianity Today about Hestens, the president of Eastern College, but how she still fits within the traditional evangelical understanding of woman in this role.
      - Conlan, John (Box 79, Folder 27, Subfolder 3)
        Folder includes a journal, Sojouners, about Conlan who was the president of the Faith-America Foundation. Also has an annotated biography of Conlan.
      - Evangelism (Box 79, Folder 27, Subfolder 4)
        Includes articles about Evangelism and culture, scans of newspaper articles, and a journal article entitled "Evangelicals and Modernity: American Evangelicalism as a Global Case Study" along with an article from the Heritage Foundation.
    - Exodus (Box 79, Folder 28)
      Folder has a cassette tape list from Exodus International-North America, an anti-homosexuality organization and a packet of their information.
    - Falwell, Jerry (Box 79, Folder 29)
      - Falwell (Box 79, Folder 29, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes scanned article about segregation, article from Thomas Road Baptist Church and a biography of Falwell. Also a newspaper article about Falwell and folder from Liberty University, "Jerry Falwell: An unauthorized profile, 1996 edition of National Liberty Journal (Conservative Christian Newspaper)." There are also a number of misc. scanned articles.
      - Falwell/AIDS (Box 79, Folder 29, Subfolder 2)
        Folder includes news transcript about Falwell's televangelism, scanned news articles, and some comments about AIDS, along with multiple copies of the same transcript discussing AIDS
    - Family Protection Act (Box 79, Folder 30)
      Folder has the text of the Family Protection Act 1981, a floor statement Albert Lee Smith, and a list of organizations against the Family Protection Act. Also an agenda for the New Right, along with scanned articles for and against the Family Protection Act.
    - Focus on the Family (1 of 3) (Box 79, Folder 31)
      This folder includes Focus on the Family a magazine article by Dobson from February 1996, scanned newspaper articles, a number of journal articles about Focus on the Family replacing Moral Majority. Also an article on Focus on the Family moving to Colorado Springs. Also an interview transcript between Ted Bundy and James Dobson, which discussed Dobson's view on corporal punishment for children. Articles about the television and radio work of Focus on the Family. Report on Mel White's Fast for Understanding against Focus on the Family. Also a transcript of interviews with Dobson.
    - Focus on the Family (2 of 3) (Box 79, Folder 32)
      - James Dobson (2 of 2) (Box 79, Folder 32, Subfolder 1)
        Folder includes ten magazines from Focus on the Family, all from 1995. Articles deals with LGBTQ+ issues, parenthood, child-rearing, and free speech. The first and last of these magazines had a Dobson column in them.
      - Other Publications (Box 79, Folder 32, Subfolder 2)
        This folder includes pamphlets from Focus on the Family, and a fact sheet about the biblical point of view on conclusions about pornography, and an article by Dobson entitled The Second Great Civil War. Finally an article entitled the "Homosexual Agenda," about community impact programming for evangelism in the public sphere, culture, and Focus on the Family.
    - Focus on the Family (3 of 3) (Box 80, Folder 1)
      - Citizens for Excellence in Education (Box 80, Folder 1, Subfolder 1)
        Information about Focus on the Family and the attempt by the religious rights to control school boards. Includes articles from the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette and Austin American Statesman.
      - Citizen/FOF Newsletter (Box 80, Folder 1, Subfolder 2)
        Issues of Citizen (the Focus on the Family magazine/newsletter) from 1987 to 1995. Also includes newsletters signed by Dobson, while the Citizen (the magazine) was written by a variety of FOF contributors.
      - FOF Video Index (Box 80, Folder 1, Subfolder 3)
        Three publications from Focus on the Family about the role of the family in daily life and cultural wars. Also a resource list and summary of all the video cassettes available through Focus on the Family in March 1995.
      - Focus on the Family Articles (Box 80, Folder 1, Subfolder 4)
        Folder includes publications both by and about Focus on the Family, including newsletters from Dr. James Dobson and articles from news organizations such as the New York Times. Anti-Focus on the Family publications were also included and a discussion of Colorado Springs as the "Vatican City of Evengalism," numerous scanned articles.
    - Feminist Backlash (Box 80, Folder 2)
      Folder includes feminist history and backlash in a timeline format from 1953-1979, which highlights the speific backlash of conservative christians.
    - Finney, Charles (Box 80, Folder 3)
      Scanned images, from a book/publication, of Charles Finney, the leader of the Second Great Awakening in America.
    - Fringe (Box 80, Folder 4)
      - The Salt and the Light (Box 80, Folder 4, Subfolder 1)